<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "{DTD_PATH}" [

]>
<!-- $Revision: 1.1.1.1 $ -->
<article>
 <articleinfo>
  <title>Dear Readers,</title>
 </articleinfo>

 <section>
  <title>&#160;</title>
  <para>
   Welcome to the fifth issue of the International PHP Magazine. Summer is
   almost over again, and with a fresh mind I was going to start working on
   some of the remaining bugs in PHP. But, that proved more difficult then I
   thought. The problem is that there are almost no reported bugs anymore, and
   if there are, they're in one of the categories that nobody else knows or
   cares about (such as ODBC, Java and OCI). So what does that mean? Is PHP
   really becoming bugfree? Well, of course it isn't. There are still some
   bugs, but they are unknown to the PHP Development team. Most of these bugs
   are in places that are not much used and does have very little chance of
   discovering, other might be introduced in PHP 4.3.3, which should be out
   already, or in the very near future. And then of course there is PHP 5 with
   it's new internals. Especially this part hasn't been tested that much by
   real users so it is very likely that there will be found quite a lot of
   bugs in there. So it might look like we're out of bugs, but there might be
   a lot of them hiding under the grass.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you want to find bugs in your own code, have a look at the last part of
   our Error Handling article. What else can you find in this issue? We have
   an article on how byte code caches work, and an accompanying benchmark with
   four caches: APC, PHP Accelerator, Turck MM Cache and Zend Performance
   Suite. We have an introductionary article on SOAP which teach you how to
   create a basic SOAP client and SOAP server. Follow ups on this article will
   be published in later issues. Steph Fox talks about new PHP-GTK
   functionality and Davey Shafik explains us ways on how to 'secure' input
   variables with HMACs.
  </para>
  <para>
    Left are the first part of a very extensive article
   on PHP 5 and OO, in this part Marcus Börger explains the new OO model
   from a users' perspective and tries to implement the methods that were
   raised in the OO Introduction article in Issue #1. The next issue will
   feature the second part of this article in which Marcus will talk about
   some more advanced features.
  </para>
  <para>
   Furthermore we have an article dealing with the under ColdFusion very
   popular FuseBox methodology applied to the PHP world and another article on
   Portability and Backwards Compatibility. The latter talks about strategies
   on how to code defensively for multiple PHP versions and provides ways on
   how to fill in missing functions from earlier PHP versions.
  </para>
  <para>
   As always, if you have any questions or suggestions, feel free to post them
   at our forum @ http://php-mag.net/forum or write to us, your editors @
   editors@php-mag.net. We hope that you enjoy this issue.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section>
  <glosslist>
   <glossentry>
    <glossterm>http://bugs.php.net/bugstats.php?phpver=4</glossterm>
    <glossdef><para>Bugs Statistics</para></glossdef>
   </glossentry>
   <glossentry>
    <glossterm>http://www.php.net/~jani/bugs-graph.php</glossterm>
    <glossdef><para>Bugs Graphs</para></glossdef>
   </glossentry>
   <glossentry>
    <glossterm>http://php-mag.net/itr/online_artikel/psecom,id,284,nodeid,114.html</glossterm>
    <glossdef><para>Leendert Brouwer: Taking PHP the OO way</para></glossdef>
   </glossentry>
  </glosslist>
 </section>
</article>
<!-- keep this comment at the end of the file
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=4 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
