<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "{DTD_PATH}" [

]>
<!-- $Revision: 1.1.1.1 $ -->
<article>
 <articleinfo>
  <title>Dear Readers,</title>
 </articleinfo>

 <section>
  <title>&#160;</title>
  <para>
   Welcome to the fourth issue of the International PHP Magazine. PHP 5 is
   coming and one of it's main features is the improved OO model, until a few
   weeks ago. Work on a few new extensions has already been started:
   simplexml, dom and xsl should be the core extensions to use, parse and
   transform XML; sqlite, simpledb and mysqli are new database extensions.
   The name 'simpledb' has not really settled, the extension will form some
   kind of abstraction for all the different database APIs including some
   additional functionality that the new OO model made possible.
  </para>
  <para>
   The MySQLi extension, yes, the MySQLi extension causes some head aches.
   Because MySQL changed the license for the version 4.x client libraries from
   LGPL (The Lesser GNU Public License) to GPL (The GNU Public License) the
   PHP project is not allowed to bundle the library anymore; even worse, they
   can not even distribute the extension anymore. Not in the core distribution
   and not in PECL <b>unless</b> PHP changes its license to GPL, which is
   something that will never happen. Actually, it gets even worse.  With the
   new licensing it is not even allowed to distribute a propriatary web
   application that relies on PHP's MySQL API (if it's using the version 4
   libraries), again, unless you distribute your application under the GPL,
   which kinda defeats the idea of 'proprietary'.  We'll illustrate how it can
   affect you with some examples:
  </para>
  <para>
   You made a large webshop relying on MySQL 4.1 functions which you wrote as
   a contract job for one specific customer, but you're not distributing
   either PHP, the MySQLi extension, the MySQL client library nor MySQL: no
   problem at all, because you're not distributing your application and thus
   are not bound to the GPL, which only covers distributing (which is weird on
   it's own, as normal non-virulent licenses usually deal with usage). Things
   change when suddenly you have to possibility to sell the same script to
   another customers. As you're now distributing the script you're bound to
   the GPL, and if you don't want to relicense your application you will need
   to buy a MySQL commercial license.
  </para>
  <para>
   During the interview we had about the licensing issues with MySQL's Open
   Source advocate Zak Greant he told us two reasons why they changed license.
   <i>"Our users now only have to deal with one non-commercial license"</i>
   and <i>"having a GPL-licensed client lets us more easily differentiate
   between a proprietary user ... and a free software user who should use the
   software under the terms of the GPL"</i>. They kinda forget there are a lot
   of Open Source developers that do not like the GPL at all because of it's
   virulent nature. MySQL with it's large user base is effectively try to
   convert its "open source" user base to the church of Emacs, and that also
   over the back of the PHP users. And that is going to far as MySQL's
   userbase only grew <b>because</b> of PHP and the bundling of its client
   library with PHP. People feel backstabbed, lines as <i>"if I knew they were
   going this way, I would never helped them"</i>. Perhaps that goes a bit too
   far, but MySQL definitely succeeded in pissing of quite a lot of PHPers,
   and also a lot off SAP DB users, and for what reason? Definitely not only for
   the two mentioned in the interview, its apparent that there is only one
   real reason: <i>"Maximize our profit, screw the users"</i>. Okay, I admit
   that that goes a little bit too far, MySQL still isn't Microsoft.
  </para>
  <para>
   What else is in this issue? As a starter we'll have a nicely filled "Ask a
   PHP Guru" section with questions from our readers.The main dish consists of
   a often requested on Secure Programming with PHP and as desert we have
   articles on Error Handling, Template Systems, cURL, XML-RPC and Jabber. Bon
   Apetit!
  </para>
 </section>

 <section>
  <glosslist>
   <glossentry>
    <glossterm>http://www.mysql.com/</glossterm>
    <glossdef><para>MySQL Website</para></glossdef>
   </glossentry>
  </glosslist>
 </section>
</article>
<!-- keep this comment at the end of the file
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=4 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
