<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "{DTD_PATH}" [

]>
<!-- $Revision: 1.1.1.1 $ -->
<article>
 <articleinfo>
  <title>MySQL and the GPL</title>
  <subtitle>An interview</subtitle>
 </articleinfo>

 <epigraph>
  <para>
   With MySQL 4.0 the licence of the client libraries changed from LGPL to GPL.
   Because this has quite some consequences for PHP users too I had an
   interview with MySQL's community advocate discussing why MySQL moved and
   what happens for PHP users that also use MySQL.
  </para>
 </epigraph>

 <section>
  <title>&#160;</title>
  <para>
   <literal>DR: Why has MySQL changed the licence for the client libraries from
   GNU LGPL (the GNU Library (or Lesser) General Public License) to GNU GPL
   (the GNU General Public License)?</literal>
  </para>
  <para>
   ZG: First, having a GPL-licensed client lets us more easily differentiate
   between a proprietary user who should buy a commercial license and a free
   software user who should use the software under the terms of the GPL.
  </para>
  <para>
   Second, rather than having multiple licenses to deal with, our users now
   only have to deal with one license: either the GPL or a commercial license.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section>
  <title>&#160;</title>
  <para>
   <literal>DR: Did you think about how the MySQL community might think of the
   license change from LGPL to GPL?</literal>
  </para>
  <para>
   ZG: Of course! Our users and community are very important to us.
  </para>
  <para>
   We expected that users who wish to use MySQL without licensing fees, but who
   do not wish to pass the freedoms that we give them with the GPL to other
   users, would be disappointed by the change.
  </para>
  <para>
   While we want our users and community to be happy, we do not believe that
   people should get the product without either commitment to community ideals
   or some cost.
  </para>
  <para>
   However, in some cases, we will grant commercial licenses at no cost (or add
   an exception to our licensing) so that we can support worthy community,
   charity or educational ventures.
  </para>
  <para>
   Community members that believe in the Free Software philosophy would, of
   course, support the change.
  </para>
  <para>
   Community members who support Open Source and dislike the GPL would not
   like the fact that their code could no longer be linked with the MySQL
   client libraries.  This aspect concerned us the most.
  </para>
  <para>
   While we support the Free Software ideals, we also support the Open Source
   community. We do not want to punish people who choose to release their code
   for the greater good.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section>
  <title>&#160;</title>
  <para>
   <literal>DR: But that is what is happening with the PHP community right now
   - we cannot distribute the new MySQL client library under its current
   licensing terms.  Does this affect the thinking inside the
   company?</literal>
  </para>
  <para>
   ZG: The PHP community has always been a great friend to MySQL and we do not
   want to hurt them (or, by side effect, our own community).
  </para>
  <para>
   We are currently working on a license exception that I hope will allow both
   Free and Open Source software to link with the MySQL client library.
   Unfortunately, this will weaken the application of the GPL to the client
   library. However, we feel that something like this is the best type of
   compromise for the Free Software community, the Open Source community and
   MySQL as a company and a community.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section>
  <title>&#160;</title>
  <para>
   <literal>DR: What about people selling PHP scripts which use MySQL, in which
   of the groups do they fall?</literal>
  </para>
  <para>
   ZG: If someone is distributing script under a closed license that uses
   MySQL, then they are creating a combined work that includes GPL-licensed
   software. They should purchase a proprietary license.
  </para>
  <para>
   If they are selling access to a site or service that use proprietary code,
   but they are not distributing the application, then they are free to use
   GPL-licensed code.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section>
  <title>&#160;</title>
  <para>
   <literal>DR: Will this exception affect distribution only, or usage
   too?</literal>
  </para>
  <para>
   ZG: If you do not distribute, you will not breach the terms of the GPL.  The
   exception is only needed for distributed code.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section>
  <glosslist>
   <glossentry>
    <glossterm>http://www.mysql.com/</glossterm>
    <glossdef><para>MySQL Website</para></glossdef>
   </glossentry>
  </glosslist>
 </section>
</article>
<!-- keep this comment at the end of the file
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=4 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
